{"tossups": [{"question": "This emperor\u2019s attempts to permanently relocate to Alexandria led Cassius Chaerea to scheme against him. This man may have caused a famine when he relocated grain ships to form a pontoon bridge between Puteoli and Baiae. This man\u2019s successor was found hiding behind a curtain after the Praetorian Guard stabbed this man thirty times. Claudius succeeded, for ten points, what Roman emperor who was accused of naming his favorite horse consul, among other insane acts?", "answer": "<b> Caligula</b> (accept<b> Gaius</b> Julius Caesar Augustus<b> Germanicus</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man was accused of staging a standardization demonstration by Merritt Smith in order to buy more time to fulfill a government order for 15,000 muskets. This man worked with Honore Blanc and Louis de Tousard to produce widely-used artillery pieces, an early concept of interchangeable parts. His most famous creation revolutionized the Southern economy by allowing for the easy removal of seeds from a certain cash crop. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.", "answer": "Eli<b> Whitney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this politician who recovered to win the 1968 and 1972 elections.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. James Bradley notes that one participant of this event was shot by a sniper less than a month after this event; that man is Frank Sousley. Felix Wheldon used a depiction of this event for the Marine Corps War Memorial. Ira Hayes and Rene Gagnon were among the six people involved in this event, which Joe Rosenthal photographed at Mount Suribachi. For ten points, name this 1945 event in which the American colors were hoisted above a Japanese island.", "answer": "the<b> raising</b> of the American<b> flag</b> on<b> Iwo Jima</b> (accept equivalents that include all 3 parts; accept Mount<b> Suribachi</b> in place of<b> Iwo Jima</b> before it\u2019s mentioned; prompt on partial answers, including Battle of Iwo Jima) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A group of these people were tried at Destrehan after trying to seize New Orleans during the German Coast rebellion. Mosby Sheppard convinced James Monroe to use the Virginia militia against a group of these people led by Gabriel Prosser. These people were prohibited from learning to read or write in many states after Nat Turner led a rebellion. For ten points, name this class of people who were the subject of the Emancipation Proclamation, which freed them.", "answer": "American<b> slave</b>s (prompt on African(-American)s; prompt on black people)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This site was allegedly built in a single night to serve as housing for Ket Mealea. A new capital was established at the Bayon after this site was sacked by the Cham people. Completed by Jayavarman VII, this site was constructed to resemble India\u2019s Mount Meru. This site was dedicated to Vishnu, but it was later converted into a Buddhist temple. A national flag depicts, for ten points, what Cambodian temple complex?", "answer": "<b> Angkor Wat</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This war included the controversial hanging of members of the St. Patrick\u2019s Battalion for desertion. The Spot Resolutions were Abraham Lincoln\u2019s Congressional attempt to discover the spot where American troops were shot near the Nueces [nu-AY-sis] River in the leadup to this war. This war ended with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which gave California to the winners. For ten points, name this war in which the United States prevailed over its southern neighbor.", "answer": "<b> Mexican-American</b> War Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This battle began with light raids against shipping during the \u201cstorangriffe\u201d period before culminating in a large scale strike on \u201cEagle Day.\u201d Beta-carotene was used in propaganda as an explanation for why one side in this battle performed better at night. This battle led to the cancellation of the invasion plan Sealion and prompted the losing side to carry out the Blitz. For ten points, name this 1940 battle where the RAF thwarted the Luftwaffe over home airspace.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Britain</b> (prompt on the Blitz before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was hosted by the subject\u2019s daughter-in-law Jane because his wife was too sick to travel. The subject of this event was 68 years old at the time, a record later surpassed by Ronald Reagan. This event included a speech of over 8,000 words delivered by a man who wore no overcoat, despite cold winds and low temperatures. For ten points, name this March 4, 1841 event, essentially the only official action of the administration of the ninth US President before his death a month later.", "answer": "<b> inauguration</b> ceremony of<b> W</b>illiam Henry<b> Harrison</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s victors followed up their success with an amphibious landing on Cavite. The<em> McCulloch</em> lost engineer Francis Randall to a heart attack in this battle. The flagship<em> Olympia</em> attacked after the signal \u201cYou may fire when you are ready, Gridley\u201d was given at the start of this battle, in which only nine Americans were wounded. For ten points, name this decisive naval battle of the Spanish-American War in the Philippines.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Manila Bay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a poem set during this war, a daughter of the nobleman Kochubei named Maria falls for the central character; that poem was inspired by a Lord Byron work about a figure in this war who served under John II Casimir. A story about the victor of this war describes a storm on the river Neva and sees Evgenii find the title statue of this war\u2019s victor staring at him. For ten points, name this war described in poems like \u201cThe Bronze Horseman\u201d and \u201cPoltava,\u201d a victory for Peter the Great.", "answer": "<b> Great Northern</b> War", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "A kingdom once located on this island drove out Dutch foreigners in the Siege of Fort Zeelandia. This island, where the Kingdom of Tungning ruled, suffered a forty-year period of martial law called the White Terror. This island was ceded to Japan in 1895 per the Treaty of Shimonoseki, and Chiang Kai-shek fled to this island after his defeat in the Chinese Civil War. For ten points, name this island controlled by the Republic of China, whose capital is Taipei.", "answer": "<b> Taiwan</b> (accept<b> Republic of China</b> or<b> ROC</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This event led to the creation of a large chain floated on wooden logs in order to block entry into a harbor. The engineer Orban helped construct the large Basilica gun for use in this event, where defenses in the Golden Horn were breached. This event led the title of \u201cConqueror\u201d to be conferred upon its victorious commander, a sultan who was just 21 years old. The Hagia Sophia became a mosque after, for ten points, what 1453 event that marked the end of the Byzantine Empire?", "answer": "1453<b> Siege</b> (or<b> Fall</b>, etc.) of<b> Constantinople</b> (prompt on other descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler briefly interrupted the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies with the creation of the Parthenopaen Republic. This ruler, who organized the Netherlands into the Batavian</b> <b>Republic, forced the Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Campo Formio on his rivals. The Confederation of the</b> <b>Rhine was organized by this man as part of a network of client states imposing an economic blockade on (*)</b> England, the \u201cContinental System.\u201d After Russia refused to agree to this man\u2019s trade policies, this man launched an 1812 invasion. For ten points, name this emperor of France.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon</b> Bonaparte (or<b> Napoleon</b> I; prompt on Bonaparte)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>While searching in this body of water in 1935, Lorenzo Hagglund found the remains of a ship that is now displayed in the Smithsonian. The gundalow</b><em><b> Spitfire</b></em><b> sank in this body of water after the Battle of Valcour Island. (+) Alexander Macomb was known as \u201cthe Hero\u201dof a battle located on this body of water, where Thomas Pringle and Guy Carleton led a 1776 attack. (*) </b> Benedict Arnold stalled the British invasion of the Hudson River Valley by winning a naval battle on, for ten points, what lake, overlooked by Fort Ticonderoga, that straddles the border of Vermont and New York?", "answer": "Lake<b> Champlain</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man attempted to become the first official to resign from the Soviet Politburo after Yegor Ligachev criticized him for allowing dissent as First Secretary. This man rose to fame by stopping the Gang of Eight\u2019s coup with a speech given (+) atop a tank. This man became the most prominent leader to sign the Belavezha Accords to establish a Commonwealth of Independent States, which formed after the (*)</b> fall of the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this first president of the Russian Federation and successor of Mikhail Gorbachev.", "answer": "Boris<b> Yeltsin</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was criticized in a political cartoon showing him pushing a black man down the throat of a reluctant abolitionist. This man, who once declared \u201cI believe this government</b> <b>was made on the white basis,\u201d argued that (+)</b> <b>territories could choose to outlaw slavery</b> <b>in the Freeport Doctrine. This author of the (*)</b> Kansas-Nebraska Act lost the election of 1860 to a political rival he defeated for a Senate seat two years earlier. For ten points, name this politician who famously traveled across Illinois debating Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "Stephen Arnold<b> Douglas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}